<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the letter directed to the author of Jus Populi by a Friend of the authors.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231777</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897610</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897610</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137225</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137225)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2505:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the letter directed to the author of Jus Populi by a Friend of the authors.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parker, Henry. --  Jus populi.</term>
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137225:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137225:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An ANSWER <hi>To the</hi> LETTER Directed to the Author <hi>OF</hi> JUS POPULI, <hi>By a</hi> Friend of the Authors.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1671</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:137225:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:137225:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An</hi> Anſwer to the letter directed to the Author <hi>of JUS POPULI,</hi> By a Friend of the Authors.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>At the firſt view of your Letter to my friend I begun to apprehend you had transformed your ſelf into an Apoſtle of Chriſt, borrowed a mantle of light, and perceiving you ſo cunning as from a plauſible miſapplication of the goſpel precepts of charity, meekneſs, patience, &amp; the like graces to ſtudy your advantages againſt a juſt and zealous indignation occaſioned by provocations which might almoſt excuſe the greateſt exceſſe, the leaſt I could expect was a non-contradicting practice; but how quickly am I releived of theſe apprehenſions? And how much more happily have you your ſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected that which, though by me evinced by cleareſt arguments, yet could not have been ſo much as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med without your complaint of <hi>reviling</hi> and <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution;</hi> if your inſinuation of a <hi>brotherly reſpect,</hi> and fair profeſſions <hi>of Chriſtian charity freedome from wrath, malice, and bitterneſſe, pity, compaſſion, a deep and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137225:3"/>affecting concernment for Gods glory and religious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement,</hi> high pretendings for <hi>humilitie, meekneſſe, and true holineſſe,</hi> a tender reguard <hi>to the union of Chriſts body,</hi> and <hi>daylie panting for an eſcape from the contentions and confuſions here below, unto theſe regions of peace and joy above,</hi> even unto the undervaluing of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> aſwell as <hi>Presbytery</hi> had been followed with an uniforme ſtraine in all other parts, they might have proven very pernicious deceivings; but ſeing that, beſide the ſlee and ſcorneful mixtures which obviouſly bewray themſelves through the whole tenor of your Letter, yow are often tranſported to the very rudeſt and fouleſt eruptions, accuſing your oppoſit as a <hi>ſcurrilous bouffon, bloudy incendiary, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of heel, equal to Beelzebub, guilty of the crime of Cham, and in hazard of Canaans curſe; unjuſt, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and cruel in reproaches,</hi> nay <hi>in the gall of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe,</hi> and finally whom in the firſt page you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coaſted as <hi>your brother,</hi> repreſenting him in the laſt <hi>as guilty of rebellion and treaſon, worthie to be made an example to all ſuch deſperat incendiaries,</hi> ſure I am that he, who cannot in theſe variant methods diſcerne your hypocriſy, muſt yet acknowledge a ſtrength of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice above its ſubtilty. However Sir in returne to the acceptable deliverance you have given me from med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling further in ſuch naughty ſtuffe, all the uſe I make of this obſervation shall be to let you ſee that you are but a man of like paſſions with us, and that though the inſolence of the Surveyer did in effect conſtraine my friend to ſome heat and sharpeneſſe, yet we do alſo know in its exigence how to cut off occaſion from them which deſire it, and to redargue your vaine glorying in the mylder &amp; calmer graces (ſo to ſpeake) by a more conſiſtent imitation, in which reſolution I addreſſe my ſelf to a short review of your Letter.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:137225:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And firſt taking God to witneſſe of theſe groanes and teares which our furious diſtempers doe draw from ſome of you, whom we ſo much perſecute,</hi> you fall into your <hi>heavy regrates to ſee the great deſignes of Godlineſſe and piety ſuffering ſo much from ſome who pretend ſo highly, and yet are more concerned for a few inconſiderable opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and niceties then for charity, meekneſſe, unity, and obedience to Authority, or for carrying on the great end for which Chriſt died &amp;c.</hi> Sir, though I may not directly call in queſtion your truth and ſincerity in this appeale, yet ſeing that all men know how that you or at leaſt moſt of that party whereunto you aſſociat did with hands lifted up to the moſt high God engage ſincerely, really, and conſtantly to own and mantaine theſe things which you do here plainely diſowne and blaſpheme, give me leave to remember you that though deceivers may deceive themſelves aſwell as others, yet God will not be mocked. If theſe <hi>furious and unchriſtian diſtempers,</hi> the object of your <hi>groanes and teares,</hi> and the <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions</hi> that you mention be indeed nothing elſe then the zealous diſſent and teſtimony of ſuch who, in the feare of the ſame high and holy Lord God whom you atteſt, dare not comply with the preſent mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt bakſlidings, and for which they have been grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly vexed, and if this your Character of their way as <hi>fury</hi> be onely either from deluſion of intereſt or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacy of humor, it is much to be feared that he who is the true and faithful witneſſe shall one day witneſſe againſt you and not for you; one thing I am perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, that whoever at preſent is a true mourner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord and as in his ſight, doth not more finde the reigning ſins of the Land and the deſolations and profanations of Gods ſanctuary to be his principal motive, then the cauſes which you aſſigne to be falſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137225:4"/>and deceitful. <hi>The great deſignes of godlineſſe</hi> do cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>ſuffer much,</hi> And O that God would as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly declare the authors of theſe ſufferring, as all men know thier beginnings. That we are the men you point at by this overconcernement for a few <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable and diſputable opinions</hi> is aboudantly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, but ſeing you are not ashamed to terme theſe things <hi>in conſiderable and diſputable,</hi> which yet doe as certainly, both by their inſtitution, and in our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, conduce to the great ends of holineſſe and happineſſe, as from Scripture and cleare reaſon they were evidently determined, and by moſt righteous and ſolemne lawes and cannons and ſacred oathes eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished amongſt us, it were unreaſonable for me to redargue your imputation, as for your prejudicial comparing of <hi>Ordinances</hi> with <hi>Dueties,</hi> and your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, by magnifying the <hi>ends</hi> of religion, to vilify its midſes as meere <hi>nicities,</hi> it is a peice of art ſo frequently practiſed by G. B. in his dialogues, and by his antagoniſt ſo ſoberly and convincingly diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that I need to adde nothing, onely let me tell you that he who truely values the death and reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Lord Jeſus, as he will aſſuredly dearely eſteeme all his purchaſe for, &amp; gifts unto his Church, ſo in theſe bacſlidings, oppoſitions, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnings which we have ſeen, he cannot but judge your <hi>comliant charity, unſeaſonable meekneſſe, eaſeful peace, cenſpiring unity,</hi> and <hi>exceſſive obedience to mans authority,</hi> to be at beſt the deluſions of a lukewarme indifferent; you ſay <hi>There is a generation who was once by appearance ſeriouſly minding their ſouls, but now are taken off that noble exerciſe;</hi> thus you diſcerne the change but cannot diſcerne its cauſes, nay of theſe you are ſo willingly ignorant that while you referre them to <hi>fooliſh and unlearned queſtions,</hi> you altogether
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137225:4"/>diſlemble who were the firſt movers; this poor Church was injoying (although with ſome infirmity) our Lords pure miniſtry and Government, and then <hi>Theſe excellent leſſons of charity, patience, humility, meekneſſe, and true holineſſe,</hi> though not in your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe application, were in ſome requeſt, when, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, as if we had been delivered from our civil bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to commit all theſe abominations, a furious tempeſt of perjury, violence, and apoſtaſy broke in upon us, not onely to the ſubverſion of the Lords work, but to the laying waſte of all religion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, what mad and untractable <hi>queſtions,</hi> and unreaſonable and violent <hi>diſputings</hi> a faithful remnant have ſince been exerciſed with the Lord knoweth, this one thing I am aſſured of that whatever advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage you may take of failings, whereunto you force them, and however you may vaunt yourſelf in empty profeſſions, yet, by their conſtant ſtedfaſtneſſe in midſt of ſo many trials, they have witneſſed a meaſure of <hi>true Charity, patience, humility, meekneſſe, and holineſſe</hi> that shall be remembred for a teſtimony for God and his truth to all generations; paſſing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your groundleſſe and childish reflexion of our <hi>ſpeaking against Biſhops,</hi> as if what you obſerve moſt we were <hi>best pleaſed with,</hi> and your more abſurd and ridiculous retortion <hi>as if we had ruined religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed Chriſt, and ſold him for the gratifying</hi> forſooth <hi>of our humors and paſſions</hi> (a ſtrange price) when as the real mony that your Bishops received for him is to be found in their coffers, the blood of his ſaints in their skirts, and under the colour of a name the very ſcandal and ſcorne of all religion in their lives; O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting alſo that moſt cenſorious calumny of our <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring, traducing, railing, forging, and publiſhing of lies</hi> which you caſt upon us without the leaſt verifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137225:5"/>and contrary to the evidence of that profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, falſehood, and perjury on your part that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſufficient to juſtify the higheſt accuſation, I wish you could yet conſider and lay to heart that it is not by the non-compliance and teſtifying of our Lords faithful members againſt corrupt bakſtiders that the <hi>ligaments of his body are diſſolved,</hi> but by the breaking of his bonds aſſunder, and caſting away of his coards from you, that your party have rebelled againſt the Lord our Head and King, and laboured for the very deſtruction <hi>of piety and true religion</hi> among us. If with theſe things you were <hi>rightly and deeply affected</hi> your ſoul would rather abhorre the wicked, who have marred and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved our true peace, then teſtify an averſion for ſuch who, at their own coſt, dare not joine in your ſinfull confederacy, &amp; in place of precipitating an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape <hi>from the contentions and confuſions here below</hi> by your aiery aſpirings <hi>to theſe regions of peace and joy above</hi> you would preferre for a time that warfare of faith and patience, againſt the wickedneſſe, ſtander, and perſecutions of this evil generation whereunto the Lord hath called us. Sir this is the path that theſe have trode who out of great tribulation are arrived, and do ſtand before the throne in white with their palmes of victory, ſinging a new ſong. Your exceſſive <hi>charity</hi> towards anungodly world, and fond and ſinful cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>peace</hi> on any termes wil but in end deceive you, the narrow way of life admits not of your latitude, &amp; heaven knowes not your comprehenſion.</p>
            <p>In the next place you <hi>are for Jeremiah's wilderneſſe,</hi> and upon the wings of the ſame fancy you flee alſo to <hi>David's retirement,</hi> why? would you ſo ſoone leave <hi>theſe aſſemblies of treacherous men</hi> which you did freely choiſe? or doth the not ceding of a ſmal afflicted party to all your impoſings ſeeme to you ſo terrible <hi>a ſtorme
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137225:5"/>and tempeſt?</hi> Nay certainly, were there no other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, the obvious eaſineſſe of the execution with your contrair forbearance is eneug he to redargue theſe your wishes either of a wretched peevishneſſe, or a worſe diſſimulation.</p>
            <p>You forbid my friend <hi>to think that all this is the effect of your zeal for Epiſcopacy,</hi> And I dare affirme that without your ſuggeſtion it had never come into his thought, the giddie inſtabilitie of the now-Biſhop of Dumblaines weak Fantaſtick braine, diſſatiſfied with both prelacy and Presbyterie, whom neither the ſmal cure of Newbottle, nor the more abſtract re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of the colledge of Edenburrough, nor his owne choice the Bishoprick of Dumblaine could formerly ſixe, and the preſent acceſſion of Glaſgow doth as little pleaſe, and yet in diſcourſe alwayes longing either for the shaddes of the grave or the reſt above, is not ſo rare a thing but you may be tainted by the ſame or the like maladie.</p>
            <p>But the cauſe of your wearineſſe is your ſolicitude <hi>for the great Biſhop of ſouls, whom</hi> my friend you <hi>ſay is doing what in him lies to depoſe from his Goverment and Kingdome,</hi> which you adde <hi>is neither in meats nor drinks, neither in Epiſcopacy nor Preſbyterie, but in righteouſneſſe and peace and joy in the holy Ghoſt:</hi> what a bold accuſation have we here? The zeal of Chriſts government and Kingdome is that which in a manner eats up my friend, he aſſerts not onely its internal and ſpiritual power, but alſo its external and viſible ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, conſiſting in theſe lawes and ordinances which our Lord by vertue of that <hi>All-power</hi> given unto him hath expreſſely appointed, and the whole ſcope of his writing is in defence of <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> and to eſtablish <hi>the peace and joy</hi> of all its followers, and yet you are confident to ſay without any reaſon,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137225:6"/>that <hi>he is doeg what in him lyes to depoſe him.</hi> It's true the Kingdome of God <hi>is neither in meats nor drinks,</hi> and thereby all the trash of your unwarranted ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies is evidently rejected, but if under this you judge the uſurpation of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> &amp; ordinance of <hi>Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> to be equally compriſed, I really feare that in the temptation the ſame errror may ſubſtitute to you the <hi>Meſſe</hi> and the <hi>Lords ſupper,</hi> or the <hi>Alcoran</hi> and the <hi>Bible</hi> with the ſame perſwaſion.</p>
            <p>The next thing that occurres is <hi>your opinion of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacie,</hi> and I am aſſured that as to this whole pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph you may already finde your ſelf ſo exactly and fully anſwered in a little treatiſe anent the late accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, that according to your owne verdict all that read it will account <hi>you deceived</hi> if you let it paſſe without a reply.</p>
            <p>As to what enſues, viz, your reſolution to <hi>forebeare both rallerie and injurie,</hi> and yet immediatlie objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>dull buffonrie,</hi> your meen and il phraſed boaſt <hi>of cauſing flaſhes of a left handed witt rebound,</hi> your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of ſeriouſneſſe which yet you onely terme <hi>a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mood</hi> and is not indeed more permanent, your promiſe not to raill, obſerved juſt aſwell as you have done other promiſes and vowes far more important, and the prejudice which you endeavour to inſinuat from the alledged <hi>general diſlike even of good Miniſters of our owne perſwaſion</hi> againſt my friends book; As to theſe things I ſay I shall content my ſelf with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked obſervation, onely as to this laſt I may affirme it upon good ground that, what ever diſlike ſome good mens over-kinde charitie or civilitie towards you, or the temper of their particular diſpoſitions may make them expreſſe of this book in certaine cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial points, yet the ſubſtance of the work both for acuteneſſe and ſoliditie hath the very conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137225:6"/>approbation of all of our way, and is alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged for ſuch by many of yours, nay further I am perſwaded that as none of your champions have as yet ventured upon its reſutation, ſo while reaſon and right remaine among men it shall alwayes be eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teemed a Maſter peice for juſt liberty and againſt ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie.</p>
            <p n="1">1. But now you begin your ontſet, and for the firſt attacque you object againſt its <hi>rallerie</hi> and <hi>reviling,</hi> the firſt as <hi>ſcurrilous, fooliſh, light, courſe, dull, flat, a puddel and kennel of putrid matter,</hi> and the latter as <hi>bitter and unexamplified railing againſt the lawes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, civilitie, and Scripture, fooliſh and Inpious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting, unjuſt, cruel,</hi> and what not; intermixing with both all the little arts of flyteing, ſuch as a ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming tenderneſſe to condeſcend on particulars, indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect inſinuations rather then plaine cenſures, a high and ſerious charge as before the great God, and then shutting up all as if you had ſaid nothing, with a <hi>Lord rebuke thee?</hi> And all this we muſt beleive to be ſaide <hi>without railing in ſober ſadneſſe,</hi> and in <hi>a humble ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Lords indignation,</hi> but as there can be no reaſon rendered to perſwade this laſt part, unleſſe it be that the words are yours, and delivered by you in one of your <hi>ſerious modes,</hi> ſo I am certaine that he who examines theſe your reflections, together with the other paſſages that I obſerved in the entrie by the rules which ye adduce againſt my friend will finde you by theſe alone equally reproved.</p>
            <p>And really ſince you muſt acknowledge that an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent neceſſitie of a retaliation hath therein tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you far beyond your ordinarie ſtraine, I almoſt wonder how you could goe thorow with ſuch a long winded invective, haling and houting my friend both before God and men, without the leaſt remembrance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137225:7"/>of the provocations he had received, but it is aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently manifeſt that however you have treated him with much ſeveritie, yet you have uſed his antagoniſt the Surveyer with a ſlighting ſilence &amp; contempt noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inferiour; waving therefore theſe idle and endleſſe ſtrivings, all that I returne to theſe your objections <hi>of rallerie and railing</hi> is firſt that your offering to dashe his <hi>whole booke</hi> and <hi>every page of it</hi> with ſcurrile ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie is an untruth ſo manifeſtly injurious, that I am perſwaded, were it not to ſerve a viſible deſigne of ſlighting arguments which you cannot anſwer, all your confidence durſt not have averred it: I graunt his animadverſions upon the ſurveyers preface with the poſtſcript of the book are by a juſt indignation proportioned to their ſubjects, but as it is only from ſome little ſeeming advantages which you thence en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to wreſte that you have aſſumed the courage to appeare againſt my friend in print, ſo I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that your attempt by ſuch a groundleſſe ſlander to diſcredit theſe ſound rational and cloſſe reaſonings wherwith the Author doth in other parts prove his aſſertions above your facultie of replying, is but a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuous artifice.</p>
            <p>Next as for your charge of <hi>railing and reviling</hi> it is ſuch an ordinary topick with all ſuch as cannot beare the freedome of truth that it very little amuſeth me, onely let me remember you that ſeing malice and not the matter is the ſting of reviling, unleſſe you had evinced this to be an ingredient in my friends repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations your clamours are but an emptie ſound: to call perjurie, violence, irreligion and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by their owne names and in due ſeaſon to teſtifie both againſt theſe abominations and their Authors and actors with that burning zeal and cordial reſentment that all men owe to the glory of God and honour of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137225:7"/>his holy name is ſo far from contradicting any goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel precept, that it is an indiſpenſible duetie, and often proves an effectuall meane for the reclaiming even of theſe who ſeeme at firſt to be the objects of its vehemencie; whither my friend was indeed acted by the power and influence of this motive I am not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to inquire, the thing it ſelf doth ſo evidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, yet if I might be heard to name <hi>evill things</hi> without the cenſure of <hi>evil ſpeaking,</hi> and if there be any place for <hi>gentleneſſe, meekneſse, and love,</hi> in teſtifying againſt ſuch perverſe tranſgreſſors, I finde it in my heart to ſay as <hi>in the ſight and feare of the great God,</hi> &amp; in <hi>a very ſerious and humble frame,</hi> with no other deſigne <hi>then that of Gods glory and my countreys good,</hi> that ſuch hath been the hainous and notorious apoſtaſie of our dayes, carried on by a perjurie ſo groſſe and blacke, and a violence ſo irrational, and ſince attended with ſuch an utter abnegation of conſcience, inſolent ſcorne of religion, and unexampled increaſe of all wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, that it may not onely juſtifie upon the matter all that my friend hath ſaid either againſt the courſe or its abettors, but upon impartial reflexion muſt of neceſſitie move every ſerious Chriſtian to hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, &amp; every ſober man to aſtonishment. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p>Jn the third place, though you goe about to ſtage him before the world for <hi>a deſpiſer of dominions and a ſpeaker evill of dignities,</hi> yet leſt the hearts of evil doers be more obdured, and their hands ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by your flatteries, and ſince I know you will no daigne to read Naphthalies plaine and unanſwerable narrative, give me leave but to touch a few particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of our backſlidings and grievances in his vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:137225:8"/>
            <p>And firſt I shall onely name that one act amongſt many, the act reſciſſorie, whereby at one blow a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, notwithſtanding their oaths and ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>to God,</hi> and their truſt for deſence of rights and liberties <hi>from the people,</hi> doe not onely overturne the work of God, but remove the very foundations of all ſecuritie amongſt men. 2. Breach of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant whereby I am aſſured we have ſeen an oath, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the moſt unanimous and heartie conſent of the people, and the moſt profound reverence and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveable preſence of God, and confirmed by all the authoritie both of Church and State, King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, violat by the ſame generation in the height of pride, ſcorne, and irreligion. 3. The perſecutions both of Mimſters and people that have inſued, what by death, banishment, impriſonment, fining, conſining and the like rigours for no other reaſon at the bottome then becauſe the ſufferers could not breake the ſame Covenant wherein both they &amp; their adverſaries ſtood equally engaged. And 4. The univerſal profanitie and wickedneſſe that theſe ſtrange bakeſlidings have either directly introduced or thereto viſibly tempted and encouraged.</p>
            <p>Sir. I doe not deſire you to take theſe things upon my truſt, no, this were not more unreaſonalbe then unneceſſary, but if you could lay aſide your affected <hi>abſtractions,</hi> and pretended <hi>elevations</hi> I doubt not but a very ſtender examination would render you ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of all that I have here aſſirmed, that in place of judging my friend his <hi>lifting up his voice to ſhew the people their tranſgreſſions,</hi> exciting of both <hi>King and people to repent and execut judgement and righteouſneſſe, the language of an incendiarie,</hi> or his denouncing of <hi>woes</hi> againſt a rebellious houſe and hypocritical ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration <hi>the office of an agent of hell;</hi> you should by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137225:8"/>hearkening, and fearing beare witneſſe to his fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
            <p>I have not in the foregoing diſcourſe taken notice of theſe ſlanders of <hi>diſlovaltie and ingratitude</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you think to make us odious, this is a theme ſo trite and toſſed on both hands, that though in this matter, I might with an hundredfold more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence demonſtrat your flatterie then you can exprobat to us the leaſt miſdemaner, yet in real duetie to his Majeſtie I choice rather to wave it. Neither as to your Bishops and clergie, a companie of men of whom all men except themſelves, are now wearied and asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, am I more inclined to medle. Onely Sir, if the unpaſſion at and disintereſſed compoſure of my heart, either as to their perſons or pettie fortunes, with all the profeſſions wherewith your ſelf do labour to perſwade your ſincerity may obtaine from you the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife that you expect of us <hi>viz, that I deſigne not your infamie but your reſormation,</hi> I would ſay that if to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the holineſſe of God and trample underfoot his truth be <hi>to blaſpheme him,</hi> if to acknowledge another ſupreme and all-determining Governour in the Church then Chriſt the Lord <hi>be to renounce him,</hi> if to ſmite his Miniſters and ſcatter his flocks be <hi>to deſtroy his Church,</hi> if to practiſe, indulge, or connive at all wickedneſſe and repute Conſcience the onely eye-ſore be <hi>to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw religion,</hi> if to put to death banish and ſpoil faithful men be <hi>to perſecut the ſaints,</hi> your Bishops and clergie, notwithſtanding of your few inſinuat and ſeeming exceptions, will ever to all diſcerning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirers be found even by your owne <hi>Characters</hi> the juſt object of all mens indignation; how then they will beare <hi>the Lords</hi> or what they may look for in the end I pray God that both you and they may in time conſider.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:137225:9"/>
            <p>Your next attempt upon my friend concerns the matter of his book, and you ſay the <hi>whole deſigne of it is to provoke to rebellion,</hi> a high charge indeed, but as ſuddenly deſerted, for <hi>you are not for raveling into this intangled matter which</hi> you conceive <hi>to be without both your owne and my friends ſphere,</hi> how Sir; are allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance and rebellion (The common concerns of the meaneſt, and the great flattering and boaſting themes of your preachers diſcourſes) ſo great myſteries? Or is this onely a declining shift like to that baſle which you deſigne by ſaying that <hi>my friends book is but Lex Rex put into another method,</hi> an allegation not more contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to its manifeſt tenor then reflecting upon the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyer whom you would have with ſo much heat and confidence to have vented things before confuted with very little notice taken of the anſwers? But the things you cannot explicat Alexander like you <hi>can cut off by two poſitions</hi> the firſt <hi>that by immemorial poſſeſſion and a long tract both of law and practiſe the King of Scotland is an abſolute Soveraigne, accountable onely to God and not to be controuled by the force of his ſubjects, but more eſpecially that the ſubjects of Scotland are bound to obey all lawes enacted in Parliament, or at leaſt to ſubmit to the enacted mulcts and puniſhments,</hi> How plentifully haſt thou declared the thing as it as? Both firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Kings of Scotland are Abſolut, and that at leaſt in King and Parliament there is ſuch an abſolut power as may in no caſe be controuled or reſiſted, are indeed the contradictions of the greateſt part of my friends book, but are contradictions alone ſufficient refutations? or shall your bare aſſertions be received againſt the moſt undeniable evidence. The certaine and cleare conſtitution of this Kingdome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of King and Parliament, the expreſſe eſtablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by uncontroverted Law, I. 6. P. 7. C. 130.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:137225:9"/>of the <hi>honour and authority</hi> of Parliament upon <hi>the free votes</hi> of the three Eſtat's thereof, the known reſtrictions of the Kings ſoveraigne power who by himſelf alone can neither make lawes, impoſe taxes, nor ſo much as put away one foot of his annexed pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony; and laſtly the frequent approven and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized reſiſtances and oppoſitions made againſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leverſing Princes, eſpecially that made by the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles againſt King James the third fully approven by the 14. Act 1. P. Ja. 4. extant in the old editions in the blacke letter as they call it, but induſtriouſly left out in that of Scheens (the tittle of the act is <hi>The propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the debait of the field of Striviling.</hi> The words af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the preface are. <hi>That the haill body of the Parliament and ilk an for himſelf declarit and concludit that the ſlaughter committit and done in the ſeild of Striviling quhair our ſoverane Lordis father happinnit tp be ſlain, &amp; uthers divers his Barronis &amp; liegis was allutterly in thair default and colourit diſſait done be him and his perverſt counſall divers tymes beſoir the ſaid field. And that our ſoverane Lord that now is and the trew Lords and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronis that was with him in the ſame field war innocent free and quyte of the ſaid ſlaughters done in the ſaid field and all perſuit of the occaſion and caus of the ſamin.</hi> Theſe are the words, and the act is declared to be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Kings great ſeal and the ſeals of part of the three eſtates) theſe I ſay as to your firſt poſition are ſuch manifeſt redargutions, that before equal judges I could undertake, upon the hazard of my life, for the aſſerting of this one point, to obtaine you convict of high treaſon as <hi>a leeſing-maker</hi> betwixt the King and his ſubjects, and an <hi>impugner of the authority of the three Eſtates:</hi> but retracting a little as to this head concerning the Kings power by acknowledging <hi>that it hath been called in queſtion,</hi> you ſay <hi>my friend hath the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:137225:10"/>honour to be the firſt who controverts the authority of King and Parliament</hi> as is evidently confirmed by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual practiſe of Scotland before year 1648. But as it is incontroverted that lawes agreed to by King and Parliament are indeed the ordinarie binding lawes until by the ſame authority they be repealed; ſo ſeing its uttermoſt import is that the ſame ſoveraigne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, which in abſolut Kingdomes is in the Prince alone, is with us divided betwixt, and ſubjected unto, both King and Parliament, it is evident that this doth no more afford us any <hi>ſpecial determination,</hi> then it doth conclude my friend to be <hi>ſingular</hi> for aſſerting the lawfulneſſe of reſiſting even the princes who are reput abſolute in caſe of their intollerable oppreſſions, wherein he hath thou ſands of concurrents.</p>
            <p>But not to trifle with you, my friend alledgeth the Kings limited power, and maketh uſe of the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Parliament in juſtification of the reſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces made by us in the yeers. 1639. And 40. And 43. whereby ſuperaddeing to our natural and common right theſe civill and poſitive priviledges he accumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth an unanſwerable vindication. As for other times wherein, the hypotheſis varying, both King and Parliament became our partie, what could be more reaſonable then to shew that even the moſt abſolut politick Empire that can be lawfully ſet up by men is lyable to theſe implyed yea indiſpenſable conditions and exceptions, which in the caſe of an inſupportable perverſion doe certainely warrant the peoples neceſſar reſiſtance, to which if you judge the inquirie into the riſe of Magiſtracie, the nature of a compact betwixt a King and his ſubjects, and the precedents of theſe two abſolut Kingdomes of Iudah and Iſrael recorded and approven in Scripture to be impertinent, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe your reaſons are above my reach. I graunt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:137225:10"/>that the ſubjects of <hi>Scotland</hi> are obliged to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with all due obedience and ſubmiſſion the ſoveraigne authoritie of King and Parliament, and that this is the onely ſupreme authority known amongſt us; but as the conſent, contract, and truſt by which this authoritie is conſtitute are by their expreſſe end and the ſuppoſed ſuperior rules of reaſon moſt certainly qualified, both as to the point of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which is by all acknowledged, and alſo as to that of ſubmiſſion by none diſowned in its conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exigence; ſo <hi>I</hi> plainly affirme that not onely there was never a ſurrender made by any people <hi>in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis</hi> diſclaiming the lawfulneſſe of reſiſtance in every caſe, and though the preſſures should be the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and violent; but that a ſurrender of that nature were in it ſelf utterly unlawful, and no wayes obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, for ſeing it were unqueſtionably contrair to the law of God for any people in the certaine imminency of viſible deſtruction to betray themſelves and their poſteritie in their lives, religion, or liberties by a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and explicit acquieſcence, it muſt neceſſarly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that either the controverted general ſurrender, by reaſon of the tacit exceptions pleaded, hath not the ſame import, or that in this reſpect it is equally ſinful.</p>
            <p>But to this you object that <hi>if ſuch ſubmiſſion be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful then they are ſelf murderers who ſuffer willingly when they are in a capacity to reſiſt,</hi> and this you ſecond with an affected <hi>Alas</hi> for the aſperſion that thence would enſue <hi>upon the glorious martyrs as ſelf murtherers.</hi> Its anſwered that he who from the meere ſenſe of ſuch a promiſed ſubmiſſion ſuffers himſelf, in a cleare ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to reſiſt, to be killed, is either a malicious or ſtupid ſelf murtherer, I nothing doubt, but ſeing that to renounce a priviledge, and to forebeare its excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:137225:11"/>are things ſo vaſtly different, that oftentimes the contradiction of the former is the latters greateſt praiſe, the cauſes and motives which induced theſe glorious witneſſes into quiet forbearing, and their voluntary and cheerful ſufferings are ſo noble and conſpicuous, that I will not ſo much as call in queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion their capacity, though for the moſt part by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence wiſely overruled, either to vindicat their immortall fame, or releive my ſelfe of your pitieful ſophiſtry. But here you think that my friend <hi>will looke to eſcape by the diſtinction of religion when it becomes a right ſetled by law from what was before it was ſo eſtablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> But ſeing it is evident that he onely makes Law an acceſſion to that liberty which we have by God and natures original graunt, your deluſive ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit that ſuggeſted unto you this apprehenſion, and your weak opinion that a right righteouſly and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily eſtablished <hi>by Law</hi> can as eaſily <hi>by a contrary Law</hi> be renverſed are equally contemptible.</p>
            <p>In the next place after a preface of your <hi>religious preferring of Gods commandments to the Kings Lawes,</hi> you fall upon an inference which you ſay my friend doth thence draw. <hi>viz. becauſe when the Magiſtrat commands what is contrary to Gods Law we are not bound to obey him, therefore when he puniſheth contrary to that ſame Law we are not bound to ſuffer,</hi> And for this indeed you treat him as Magiſterially as if he were really that <hi>ſchoole boy</hi> to whom you do dully reſemble him, but ſparing to inquire where it is that you do finde him barely delivering this conſequence, and not being permitted in this place to explaine how that, regard to the Prince, his place &amp; character, and the general ends thereof, and how that many conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of prudence, charity, and patience may in lighter occaſions perſwade to ſubjection, where its
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:137225:11"/>proper and formal reaſon hath no immediat force, I shall onely ſay that the comparing of the limitation of our obedience with the caſe of our ſuffering is of excellent uſe, in as much as it sheweth, firſt, that as a peoples indefinit ſurrender though chiefly reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their obedience doth nevertheleſſe imply its tacit exceptions, ſo the ſeeming generality of the ſame ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render is no argument to exclude all conditions in the point of ſubjection, next that ſeing a diſcretive judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is allowed to the people in the matter of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, there can be no reaſon wherefore in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuffering a thing far more obvious and dignoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible the ſame should by the men of your way be ſo much decryed. Thirdly ſince it is certaine that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to ſuffering was directly commanded by God, and conſented to by the people onely for the ſecuring of our obedience, it may well be conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that as in inferiour unjuſt ſufferings our reſiſtance is moſtly reſtricted not by vertue of our formal obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to ſubjection, but by the forementioned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences, ſo when by notorious and inſufferable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions all theſe are cut off and both <hi>the place</hi> is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forefeited, <hi>prudence</hi> befooled, <hi>charitie</hi> rendred deſperat, and <hi>patience</hi> turned into ſtupiditie, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of reſiſtance muſt of neceſſitie be conceded. As for the reaſon of diſparitie by you adduced, <hi>viz.</hi> That in the caſe of the Kings ſinful command Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termand of our obedience is ſuppoſed to be cleare, whereas our ſufferings are not countermanded though he punish unjuſtly, I shall not reply to you that in the caſe of a ſtupid caſting away of life or liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie even ſufferings aſwel as ſinful obedience are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly countermanded, but the thing I would have you to advert to is, that ſeeing it is not ſo much the obligation as the right and liberty of defence which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:137225:12"/>we plead for, and ſeeing in the caſe of intollerable ſufferings the ſame is no leſſe clearly warranted then ſinful ſuffering appears to be countermanded, the difference by you aſſerted is but claudicant and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient.</p>
            <p>But now <hi>you are wearie of tracing my friends poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> and truely conſidering how ſamely you have done it, I wonder you have traced them ſo far, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let me tell you that if you shall be pleaſed to give me any further provocation upon this ſubject, I here offer to make good all that my friend hath aſſerted in maintenance of the Peoples rights and liberties to the moſt critick, if impartial, of your adherents.</p>
            <p>You adde that it is your <hi>chiefe deſigne to prove that matters of Religion are not to be decided by the ſword.</hi> Pray Sir, ſpeak plainly, you know and are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that we are neither for the <hi>propagation</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, nor <hi>determining in its matters</hi> by the ſword, all that we maintaine is that in the caſe of unjuſt ſuffering for the ſake of Religion, however the honour and excellency of the cauſe may much allay a mans ſmart, and make him cheerfully to undergo it, even to a not-accepting, &amp; ſeeming contempt of deliverance; yet he hath the Privilege of common defence no leſſe then in other occaſions, which if he finde the intereſt of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions preſervation to concurre it ought ſo much the more to animat his reſolution, now if <hi>this be a ſpirit totally different from Chriſt's</hi> who came not to deſtroy the Law but teacheth us to fulfil all righteouſneſſe, I leave it to your own ſecond thoughts. <hi>Christ's Kingdom is</hi> indeed <hi>not of this World</hi> &amp; that he did moſt evidently demonſtrat by telling that if his Kingdom were of this World then would his ſervants fight, and therefore ſeeing that even for his owne reſcue he had not called them when he might have had ten Legions of Angels
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:137225:12"/>upon his deſire, that his Kingdome was not from thence could not be doubted; but to turne this over as if our Lord had ſaid, <hi>Becauſe my Kingdome is not of this World, therefore my ſervants may not fight,</hi> ſo much as for their own preſervation, is a manifeſt ranverſing of both the text and the truth.</p>
            <p>Next you tell us, <hi>That to ſtirre up to Religions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence by its value is but an ignorant though plauſible miſtake;</hi> but as your perſwading us to abandon the maintenance of Religion by the <hi>firmeneſse of Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and our Lords Kingdome,</hi> ſounds more like the Turkish errour of unalterable fate, then to a Chriſtian deference to divine providence, which alwayes admits of our lawful concurſe; and as this your doctrine is moſt palpably contradicted by the conſtant practice of the whole Chriſtian World, who with might and maine do arme for, and ſtand to the defence of Religion againſt the invaſion of infidels; ſo your extenuation <hi>as if the hazard of our lives, fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and liberties were not to be regarded,</hi> is but an inſipide deceitful affectation: if God in the diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his holy and wiſe providence eſpecially by bringing us under the power of men, ſubject us to ſuffering and call for a teſtimonie, it is moſt certaine that neither ought Religions concern to diſcourage nor the conſiderations of life, fortune, and liberty in the leaſt to demurre us, but thence to inferre, that in caſe either a Nation or a Perſon (for as to the point in general there can be no difference) be unjuſtly and violently invaded for Religion, they ought without further care in a tempting confidence, <hi>that Religion cannot be indangered by the Worlds oppoſition,</hi> and a baſe and unrequired abjection of themſelves and their intereſts foolishly throw Religion and all down head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto the rage of in jurie and tyrannie, is a doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:137225:13"/>too agreeable to the Devils temptation for to deceive any rational man. The truth of the matter therefore is, that as we ought neither to flight nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend too much our own prejudice, ſo it is from patient and not by ſtupid ſufferings that our <hi>holy profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> receives the advantage.</p>
            <p>But to this you ſubioine your grand diſcovery <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>the great deſigne of the goſpel is to elevat our mindes to a noble contempt of the world, and a juſt diſreguard of our bodies, &amp;c.</hi> whence perſwading <hi>patience, truſt in God, and ſubmiſſion to his will</hi> you conclude, <hi>let all the world judge whether ſuffering ſo like to it or fighting ſpeaking out a froward and impatient minde do best agree with this temper and deſigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, if I may ſo far digreſſe under your conduct, I would ſay in the firſt place, that the great deſigne of the Goſpel is to reconcile ſinners unto God through Jeſus Chriſt who of God is made unto us wiſdome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, and redemption; your repreſenting it by <hi>elevations of minde and neglectings of the body</hi> doth ſavour too rankely of that dangerous er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of making the righteouſneſs of Chriſt a meer help to ours, and the Goſpel onely the perfection of mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, next I ſay that ſetting aſide the neceſſity and beauty of every duety in its ſeaſon, if it were all your intention to commend ſuffering above fighting, I would not onely with you in your judicious diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning preferre <hi>patient</hi> ſuffering to <hi>paſſionat and impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient</hi> fighting (things which I ſuppoſe were never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore compared) but even in humanity, let be in Chriſtianity, advance the palme of a well compoſed, and reſolved patience; above the laurel of a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like though righteous triumph. But becauſe your riſe taken from the deſigne of the Goſpel doth plainly enough inſinuat that it is the particular fightings for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:137225:13"/>religion which you go about to decry, it is in thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>that I deſire more diſtinctly to know your conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; ſeing the ſame arguments of heavens hope, and this worlds contempt do equally mitigat the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and depretiat the worldly prizes of all war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res whatſomever, to admit that Religion doth allow all other lawfull warres except what is levied in its owne defence is evidently in an exceſſe of ſelf denial to make it deny nay deſtroy it ſelf, but ſeing all the pretenſions that we have here repeated out of the late dialogues of <hi>the Goſpels deſigne, ſpirituality of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the probability by ſufferings of advance to the Goſpel, and carnality of fighting</hi> are already ſufficiently diſcuſſed by their anſwerer I shall at preſent content my ſelf to paſſe them with a few remarks. As 1. That ſeing you are upon the perſecuting ſide (pardon to truth the uneaſineſſe of the expreſſion) or at leaſt do exhort to patience your antagoniſts &amp; not your parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in the ſame cauſe, you muſt permit us to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend deſign aſwel as truth in all your reaſonings 2. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though if the will of God be ſo the Goſpel excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly inſtruct to ſuffering, yet it neither condemneth lawful warres, nor is it imaginable wherefore defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive wars being allowed, a defenſive warre upon the moſt injurious provocation <hi>viz.</hi> perſecution for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion should not be accounted moſt righteous. 3. That though patient ſuffering and holding faſt of his name under perſecution be a ſtrong and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing evidence of our faith and hope, yet as our Lord by retaining the diſpenſation in his owne hand hath onely commanded unto us the manner of our ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and having expreſly permitted flight hath not engaged us to run upon it, ſo to uſe the right and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity which God giveth of ſelf defence without furious paſſion or revengeful deſigne can neither be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:137225:14"/>reprehended nor ſuſpected, I know <hi>a wicked man may fight couragiouſly for Chriſt,</hi> and ſo have ſome blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers and Atheiſts ſuffered conſtantly, but ſeing we have ſeen the ſame perſons, with the ſame ſtrength of grace, both offer themſelves reſolutly, and ſuffer in teſtimony even of their fighting moſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, you muſt pardon us to reguard the truth more then your cavilling exceptions.</p>
            <p>But in the following ſection you goe about to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove defenſive wars againſt perſecutions for religion by <hi>our Lords precepts and practiſes, who</hi> you ſay <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thoſe who ſhould ſuffer jor him.</hi> And why not? Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely they are pronounced bleſſed and they shall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>But he threatned them that drew the ſword,</hi> well, <hi>for him</hi> you dare not adde, and <hi>againſt him</hi> is not doubted, nay ſuppoſe it had been againſt Peter at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting his perſonal deliverance it had given you no advantage, ſince he alſo rebuked him as Satan for deſiring him to ſpare himſelf; <hi>he bleſſed likewiſe the peace makers entituling them the children of God,</hi> and our hearts deſire is that God would raiſe up to us a true peace-maker, to reduce you unto wiſdome, whoſe wayes are wayes of pleaſantneſſe and all her paths are peace. <hi>The incendiaries of warre are</hi> indeed <hi>no where pronounced happie and the boutefeus of rebellion are</hi> certainly <hi>the children of him who was a murtherer from the begining;</hi> but, Sir, is this fair dealing? The queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that you move and have to prove is, that my friend is an incendiarie and boutefeu and behold with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reaſon offered, you not onely conclude him but condemne him, it were undoubtedly as eaſie and aboundantly juſt for me to inquire <hi>where perjurious perſecuters are pronounced happie, &amp;c,</hi> but I will not ſo much as retort or retaliat with ſuch expreſſions, <hi>ſuch as breath out warre and crueltie know not what ſpirit,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:137225:14"/>they are of</hi> and our prayer to God is that they who <hi>brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out threatnings and ſlaughter againſt us</hi> terme juſt defence and neceſſarie reſiſtance <hi>war and crueltie</hi> may at length have their eyes opened, <hi>All in the Goſpel-diſpenſation is truely gentle and peaceable;</hi> and yet of all things in the world it hath been moſt reproached for tumult and ſedition; but the great conſolation of all its followers is, that <hi>its author the God of peace</hi> will one day make known all falſe pretenders, <hi>and its Lord the Prince of Peace</hi> for their perſecutions here will in the end bleſſe with everlaſting peace all its true lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, when according to the excellent order of the Goſpels rule of peace the Kingdome of God shall be fully revealed <hi>in righteouſneſſe firſt,</hi> and then in <hi>peace and joy in the holy ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you ſay that <hi>all this viz</hi> a non-reſiſtance of, and ſubmiſſion to perſecution <hi>was ſignally confirmed by our maſters unexampled ſufferings,</hi> and yet you know ſo well that the free and voluntarie ſufferings of our Lord are in themſelves no leſſe unexampled then uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitable, and that it is the manner and not the matter thereof that we are to follow, that I cannot but doubt your ſinceritie, Chriſt not onely refuſed the aide of the ſword but came into the world <hi>willinglie,</hi> went up to Ieruſalem <hi>ſtedfaſtly,</hi> expoſed himſelf <hi>knowingly,</hi> and laſtly would not aske the <hi>aſſiſtance of legions of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> readie at his deſire that the Scriptures ſignifieing how <hi>that he ought</hi> to have ſuffered might be fulfilled; and is it poſſible that you can think, that theſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick acts are for our imitation? But you ſay that <hi>he entailed perdition on theſe that ſhould draw the ſword</hi> to wit <hi>all theſe that are not warranted to doe it by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrat.</hi> How long will you love vanitie and ſeek after leeſing? Our Lord in that place doth moſt plainely, for the averting of <hi>Peter's</hi> unſeaſonable zeal, and the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:137225:15"/>comforting of all his Diſciples, denounce that <hi>all theſe who take the ſword unjuſtly ſhall periſh by the ſword, and. Rev.</hi> 13.10. we have the parallel place more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet downe <hi>he that killeth with the ſword muſt be kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the ſword</hi> (ſpoken of perſecuting Magiſtrats aſwel as others) <hi>Here is the patience and the faith of the Saints,</hi> And yet you have the confidence to ſmooth it over as if this ſad doome had been pronounced not onely againſt Peter but all ſuch as shall be by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of oppreſſion conſtrained to their owne defence.</p>
            <p>You adde that <hi>he witneſſed that good confeſſion before Pilat that Caeſar needed apprehend no hazard from his Kingdome, ſince it not being of this world was not to be fought for.</hi> And doe you indeed think that this is the emphaſis of that <hi>good confeſſion viz</hi> to ſatiſfie Ceſars unjuſt fears? O perverſe flatterie! The excellent goodneſſe of our Lords confeſſion cannot but be ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relished by every ſerious Chriſtian to lye in theſe words <hi>thou ſaieſt that I am a King to this end was I borne and for this cauſe came I unto the world that I ſhould beare witneſſe unto the truth,</hi> how then are you not as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamed not onely to wreſt it unto the pitieful intereſt of Princes; but to miſconſtrue the whole paſſage as if our Lord in purging himſelf by a voluntarie and free forbearance of the affectation of a worldly Kingdome did in effect diſowne all defenſive armes to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging and ſtrengthening of the moſt bloudie ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans.</p>
            <p>You think it ſtrange that through the whole Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel we should meet with repeated bleſſings on theſe that ſuffer, but never one upon ſuch as fight; but if our Lord having declared that he came not to deſtroy the Law of righteouſneſſe did accommodat his incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements to his Apoſtles, unto the diſpenſation fo his providence under which for the greater glorie of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:137225:15"/>power of his free grace he thought good to gather and traine up his Church, should you or any elſe be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſtumbled; for my part when I reflect upon both the ſufferings and grace of the primitive times and how the Lord did order them, I rather wonder at that admonition by you obſerved that they should ſell their coats to buy ſwords; but you ſay <hi>had the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples underſtood this of the material ſword either their prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes or writings ſhould have had ſome veſtiges of that ſenſe,</hi> by the which very argument a man may as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily deny that the <hi>Purſe</hi> there ſpoken of is to be taken for a material one; but ſeing the tenor of the context and relation made by the Lord to their former miſſion doe exhibit the meaning with that evidence as cannot be convelled, for want of an unoccaſioned confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, I go on to examine the reſt of your gloſſe upon the place; and taking notice <hi>that the Diſciples at the time by preſenting two ſwords did ſhew that they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Lord to ſpeake of a material ſword</hi> you ſay <hi>that by his anſwer it is enough, which cannot relate to the two ſwords produced no wiſe enough for eleven perſons, he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects their error &amp; breaks off their purpoſe as if he had ſaid, enough of this, or no more of it, ſince he ſawe they miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood his former words of a ſword.</hi> Thus rather then to aſſent to truth you would have our Lord by ſuch a ſtop tacitly to acknowledge his own inadvertency, but the paſſage is too obvious to be thus abuſed, in aſmuch as our Lord having before both ſignified and prepared for his owne imminent departure, forewarnes them by the neceſſitie, <hi>of a purſe and a ſword</hi> of the ſtraits and dangers that would enſue, whereupon they, its like, out of their blind and forward deſire to have him delivered from the hand of the jewes lay hold on his words and shew him two ſwords, probably with a confident remembrance of his former miracles, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:137225:16"/>this their precipitancy our Lord according to the meek and ſweet compoſure to his patience now entering upon his ſufferings thinks fit to reſtraine with this short correction <hi>it is enough,</hi> i. e. <hi>it is enough at this ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> there muſt be no reſiſtance in my voluntary ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering: whether then yours or this explication be the more genuine I referre it to the diſcerning of all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding men.</p>
            <p>But yet <hi>from all this</hi> you ſay <hi>it will eaſiely appeare to one who examines the matter without prejudice whether ſuffering or fighting have the cleareſt characters of Chriſts meekneſſe.</hi> Sir though the nature of warre being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, the compariſon of ſuffering and fighting in the point of meekneſſe ſeems almoſt to be inept, yet if you will be pleaſed to advert how that our Lord aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in his victorious triumph as in his loweſt ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings is repreſented in the <hi>Revel:</hi> under the ſame figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the <hi>Lambe,</hi> its like you may come to underſtand that that calme ſtaiedneſſe of minde, which by all is reput the trueſt marke of the nobleſt courage, may in a Chriſtian champion be yet further advanced and beautified with his Maſters meekneſſe.</p>
            <p>Your laſt argument againſt defenſive armes upon the account of religion is <hi>that the doctrine of ſuffering tends moſt to the recommending of the Chriſtian religion to all Princes and Stats, whereas the doctrine of defence may prepoſſeſſe their mindes with the deepeſt prejudices, &amp;c.</hi> Thus to carry your cauſe you care not what you ſay, this argument can have no proceſſe unleſſe we ſuppoſe in all Princes and States a moſt irrational a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion for religion, <hi>viz,</hi> ſuch as cannot endure that it should pretend to any manner of right or comport with its profeſſors at a lower rate then the abſolute ſubjection of their lives and liberties; upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and yet without the leaſt check of correction,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:137225:16"/>you beſtow upon it a whole long paragraph. But ſeing that all we plead amounts to no more then that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion the great inſtructer of righteouſneſſe may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of all right, and that its high honour may not depreſſe men below the condition of ſlaverie, you muſt pardon me to think your inſinuation more odious then obliging.</p>
            <p>But for to mend your errour you adde <hi>that indeed the Alcoran incites to kill all who are not Muſulmans but our holy profeſſion rejects carnal weapons from its defence.</hi> Who heard ever ſuch diſtraction? Can we not deteſt the Mahumetan Barbaritie of forceing religion by the ſword, unleſſe we lay open all Chriſtendome to their rage and crueltie? Or is your minde ſo blinded by your deſigne that you could not perceive the fair and rational midſe of the lawfulneſſe of ſelfe defence againſt intollerable oppreſſion, and that aſwell yea rather when inflicted for, and levelled to deſtroy religion, then in the caſe of any other unjuſt pretenſe, without either impinging upon the turkish violent propagations on the one hand, or betraying the cauſe of religion by a baſe ſtupiditie upon the other? <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> certainly in it ſelf <hi>is no occaſion of warres,</hi> but if your Muſulemans make it ſo, muſt we therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon both it and our ſelves to their pleaſure? And if unjuſt <hi>warres doe ariſe from your luſts</hi> may not a juſt oppoſition very well conſiſt, nay be warranted by <hi>that which injoynes the mortifying of them all?</hi> Sir your lapſes here are ſo groſſe and rawe againſt all right and reaſon that I am ashamed to draw forth againſt you poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive concluſions.</p>
            <p>To theſe things you ſubjoyne the praiſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>For the allegeance towards Princes and peaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse towards fellow ſubjects which it teacheth, thence commending both its innocency &amp; the great ſecuritie it gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:137225:17"/>unto all ſocieties,</hi> but ſay you, <hi>the doctrine of reſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance will change its whole viſage ſo that this day-ſtarre whoſe aſpects are benigne will look like a fierie-eomet bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing warres, &amp;c.</hi> Sir, this charge appeares to be ſo weightie that I willingly wave its extravagance, that I may meet with its reaſon, <hi>For</hi> (you continue) <hi>if this principle be drunke in by Chriſtian ſocieties they may for ever diſpair of peace, ſince all cannot be of one mindein matters of Religion, and the ſide or partie oppreſsed would undoubtedly raiſe ſturs.</hi> But ſeeing the principle you inveigh againſt is in effect none other then that right of ſelf-preſervation moſt deeply engraven in natures tables, to which we plead, that Religion according to its dignitie, in the caſe of perſecution, intending the injurie, may make no exception, is it not evident that your arguing againſt this Privilege as a novel ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious conceit is in effect nothing elſe ſave a colourable pretext, thorow which Religion is onely ſtruck at as in its nature altogether <hi>unpeaceable and the very ſeed of endleſſe contentions?</hi> But the matter is plaine, the right ſelf-defence is the principal reaſon both of the inſtitution and continuance of Government, Religion in it ſelf is one, ſimple, moſt pure, and peaceable; all contended for, is, that ſuch as by embracing of it do become partakers of the higheſt bleſſing may not therefore forfeit the moſt common rights, if this be to turne <hi>this heavenly and benigne ſtar of Religion unto a fiery blazing comet,</hi> and not rather by maligning it, with all the perverſities of its adverſaries, unleſſe it be made obnoxious to all their injuries, either to render it odious to Princes, or lyable to all the arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie impoſings and perſecutions of tyrannie, let all men judge; it is true that by reaſon of mans corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>a harmony in Religion is ſcarce to be attained,</hi> but becauſe error and irreligion will alwayes be ſtirring,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:137225:17"/>perſecuting, and provoking to ſtirrs and tumults, muſt therefore the truth and its profeſſors be ſtupidely ſubmitted to their luſt and rage? You ſay, <hi>That even we ourſelves would ſinde it a hard pull to governe at this rate, ſpecially if we keep up our quarrels both at toleration and moderation.</hi> How? Would we finde it ſo hard a task by keeping faith to retaine both obedience and peace, and by pleaſing God to pleaſe all men? That this was the true Criſis of our affairs in the late revolution I believe thouſands do now ſee, who then would not, as for your objecting of our quarrels at tolleration and moderation, is not this a ſtrange en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, that becauſe we cannot ſtretch to a compliance with all the preſent evil courſes, therefore even our juſt hatred at error and hereſie ſpecially ſeeing it was ſo very diſſoyal and ſeditious muſt alſo be reckoned to our diſadvantage.</p>
            <p>After this you tell us <hi>that from this principle there were no peace to be expected from Papiſts.</hi> And to deale fairly and shortly with you I freely accord that if the Papiſts did hold the truth, and were therefore intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erably perſecut, they might very lawfully reſiſt in their owne neceſſarie defence; but ſince they both practiſe groſſe idolatrie and other abominations, and are alſo reſtleſſe in their wicked machinations, it is evident that they could as little reclaime againſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved punishment under the notion of perſecution, as at preſent they are largely indulged.</p>
            <p>For a concluſion then you tell us <hi>that the doctrine of patient peaceable ſuffering excludes all hazards, and is therefore more for the intereſt of mankinde and peace of ſocieties.</hi> And certainly that which ſurrenders all hath no hazard to apprehend. But if the Chriſtian world had been of your opinion, how had its religion long ſince been ſwallowed up of Turciſme? And if our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the firſt dawnings of reformation had no af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:137225:18"/>a noble conflict of martyrdomes and perſecutions diſcerned the times, and laid hold on the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I am ſure in all probabilitie Scotland had been to this day as France, and worſe, and the United as the Spanish Netherlands, and all Germainie under one cloud. If you doe therefore judge Religion to be of the intereſt of mankinde doe not deny it the libertie of a right nor deprive it of its juſt priviledge, ſeing on the one hand this is not more iniquous and in effect impoſſible, then on the other your pretendings <hi>to peace</hi> by ſuch arguing doe viſibly tend to the ruine of <hi>truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having gone this far with my friend you deſire him <hi>to look backe ſeriouſly upon theſe two different methods of advancing religion that he may ſee whether of them will preponderat.</hi> But Sir if I may prevaile with you in any thing, I earneſtly obteſt you to uſe more ingenuitie, did ever we aſſert or practiſe the advancing of religion by fighting? Or did we at any time in order to this end ſo much as lay ſuffering and fighting in one bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance? Or laſtly muſt I againe inculcat that all that we maintaine, is, that in caſe of violent perſecution for religion the oppreſſed may lawfully aſſume their owne defence as upon the provocation of any other injurie whatſomever.</p>
            <p>After this, diſſembling your knowledge of our averſion for war, not capable to be ingaged but by manifeſt extremitie, you pleaſe your ſelf with ſome few ſpeculations of the advantages of peace and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages of war: but ſeing ſuch little arts are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently diſcuſſed by the ſimple noticing, let us hear how you make it out by Scripture inſtance <hi>that figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is not a methode approved of God for advancing his cauſe,</hi> And for eſchewing cavill, I am here willing to think <hi>that by advancing of his cauſe</hi> you onely mean the preſervation of religion and its profeſſors againſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:137225:18"/>their perſecutors, and your firſt inſtance is of the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lits who while in Egypt long oppreſſed in their religion and libertie though very numerous and in a probable capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie yet made no attempt by force for their owne deliverie.</hi> But pray Sir doe you think the Iſraelites in their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage could have foughten with weapons when they wer denyed ſtraw? Or doth not ſuch headleſs quibling as manifeſtly conclude that becaus of their conſtrained ſubjection under their ſeveral oppreſſors the time of the judges, therefore their after vindications of their liberty were ſinful, but the truth is ſeing that if God ſo ordered the matter in his providence as the Iſraelits neither did nor could endeavour their owne libertie, that he might in his owne way manifeſt his glory, your inference that therefore either they might not have done it lawfully, or that we are obliged to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat their forced and ſimple omiſſions is not worth the noticing, and really this reaſoning is ſo weake and piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that I am almoſt ashamed to have repeated it.</p>
            <p>The next inſtance which you promiſe <hi>ſhall be yet ſtronger</hi> (as truely it had need) is taken from the ten tribes non reſiſtance to Jeroboams defection, but knowing that they willingly walked after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and that if they had had the ſmalleſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of that zeal for religion which they teſtified for their owne liberty, they had not ſo tamely complied in that bakeſſiding, you recurre to the ſilence of the Prophets telling us that <hi>if popular reformation had been the peoples ductie certainly they had exhorted to it.</hi> Well Sir, is this your ſtronger reaſoning? The Prophets by all the pains and induſtrie they did uſe could ot awake this ſtubborne people to repentance, and yet becaus forſooth they did not expreſſely excit them <hi>active</hi> to reforme, who were in effect to have been its only objects, from this you conclude that the thing was not their duetie.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:137225:19"/>
            <p>But you adde <hi>that though Achab added the idolatrie of Baal to the ſin of the Calves, yet Eliah never ſturred up the people to armes,</hi> is not this ſolid arguing? The people of Iſrael had at this time ſo deeply revolted that when the Prophet put it home to them, if the Lord be God follow him, but if Baal then follow him, they anſwered not a word, yea afterward when he was forced to flee from Jezabels rage he thought he had been the only ſeeker of the true God left in Iſrael, &amp; yet without any reguard to a moſt manifeſt unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liehood you think becauſe the Prophet did not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterouſly call them to it, that therefore (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all that my friend hath ſaid for it) natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reformation was not their part, the abſurditie of which argument is ſo much the more groſſe, that even in the ſame Prophet and people after a due pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration you may finde your aſſertion contradicted, in aſmuch as immediatlie upon the backe of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the Lord to be God Elijah <hi>ſaid unto them</hi> (the King being preſent) <hi>take the Prophets of Baal, let none of them eſcape, &amp;c.</hi> a verie probable intimation that not onely they might have done it, though the King had countermanded, but that even without Eliah's exhortation it had been nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide their duetie.</p>
            <p>From Iſrael you paſſe to Judah and finding there the like defections you repeat to us the ſame obſerves, but ſeing that all the Prophets doe teſtifie aloud of the univerſall bakeſlidings of that people togither with their Kings, and Iſaiah and Ieremiah doe expreſly and frequentlie complaine that none did call for juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, or plead for truth, &amp;c. And that they were not valiant for the truth, as it is evident that they are thereby <hi>charged with lukewarmeneſſe in the cauſe of God,</hi> ſo it ſeemes that for the generality they were no leſſe perverſe in heart then their ringleaders in theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:137225:19"/>as theſe very perſecutions perhaps of faithful diſſenters under Manaſſe whom you vainly repreſent <hi>as ignorant of our politicks</hi> may very plainly evince? And as for that of <hi>Libnah</hi> ſeing the Scripture expreſly ſaith, that they did revolt from under the hand of the King (and not from under Judah as the Edomits did) <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had foreſaken the Lord God of his Fathers,</hi> your queſtioning its approbation, becauſe of the not enſuing of the like practiſe, is both preſumptuous againſt Scripture evidence, and derogatorie from the praiſe of all more noble and rare exploits.</p>
            <p>Having propoſed your inſtances as we have heard, you ſeale them with a grave <hi>truely you muſt conſeſſe theſe inſtances to be ſtrong,</hi> and really ſince you deale ſo obligingly with my friend as not to force him by any reaſon, I beleeve if the thing were a matter of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement he would in civility cede it, but ſeing it is truth we contend for, without further canvaſſing of what you ſubjoine <hi>of the nature of Moſes diſpenſation or the Goſpels call to the Croſſe, I frankely leave it</hi> as you do <hi>with all free mindes to conſider</hi> whether your poor blinde negatives be of any moment to preponderat that cleare light of reaſon which shineth in our aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and is confirmed both by old teſtament exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and new teſtament approbations, as my friend &amp; the anſwerer of the dialogues do evidently hold out.</p>
            <p>As to your enſuing ſection <hi>anent the firſt ages of the Church their unacquaintedneſſe with this doctrine and your boaſting Hiſtorical obſerve, that until Pope Gregory the 7th his dayes it was unheard of in the Church, with your endeavours to render it odious by the patrociny of Cannoniſts and Jeſuits</hi> it is ſo exactly the ſame with the diſcourſe of the dialogues, and is by the anſwerer ſo clearly diſcuſſed, that I am not affraid to oppoſe his ſingle reply to your vaine repetitions; one thing I muſt tell you, that ſeing you cannot deny that about and after
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:137225:20"/>Conſtantines dayes when Chriſtians arrived to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſiſtency and better capacity not only did Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine himſelf with the expreſs approbation &amp; aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſence of the Godlieſt teachers in theſe times fight againſt Licinius for his perſecutions, but alſo both the oppreſſed Chriſtians in the eaſt did aſſert by armes the liberty of the Goſpel againſt Jovius, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximinus and at other times and in other places they implored the aid of Chriſtian and orthodox Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours againſt pagan and Arrian perſecuters, your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to put a tashe upon <hi>theſe practiſes as criminal</hi> which yet all the after ages of the Church have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proven, and to evade by ſaying <hi>that the doctrine was not then owned</hi> which was onely not expreſſely maintained, becauſe not contradicted, is nothing at all ingenuous; &amp; therefore ſince it is certaine that even the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent truths have been lyable to the fouleſt abuſes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your odious dating of the doctrine of reſiſtance from a notorious Papall rebellion, nor your futilous eſſay to make men beleeve that its onely propagators were the Popes Paraſits do deſerve any further notice.</p>
            <p>And now we are come to the cloſe of your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherein conceiting that <hi>either you have made ſure our conviction,</hi> or diſcovered <hi>our cure to be with men impoſſible</hi> you think good to give a teſtimony to your ſelf, which I am perſwaded, conſidering the folly or falſehood of the poor purpoſe that I have peruſed, among all that have written on the ſubject you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve leaſt. But if you miſſe of your owne praiſe, you are reſolved my friend shall fare no better, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as if this were the firſt of it, you pretend conſtraint for <hi>one ſevere word</hi> to tell him, whom al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the beginning you termed <hi>an agent of hell, as evill as Beelzebub,</hi> that you do feare him <hi>to be in the gall of bitterneſſe,</hi> Sir, although ſuch reproaches be to me very light, yet I wish that for your own ſouls good
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:137225:20"/>you would ſeriouſly ponder that to undervalue the grace, and deſpiſe the glory of the work and cauſe of God that we have ſeen in the land, to ſtrengthen the wicked in their wickedneſſe, &amp; adde affliction to theſe whom for conſcience onely men do perſecute, are characters of this wretched and woful ſtate, equal (if not worſe) to what appeared in him againſt whom theſe words were firſt pronounced, whether your preceeding diſcourſe and ſubſequent ſtricture in this place againſt the cauſe of God do partake of theſe evils I leave it with your ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Your laſt obſerve is upon my friends poſtſcript, occaſioned by the Bishop of <hi>St Andrews</hi> his affirming in a ſermon <hi>that the ſubjects lives were more the Kings then their own,</hi> and his paſſage ſo moves your ſpleen, that it is evident you reſolve to be behinde with him in nothing, and therefore after you have charactered him <hi>as inſolent, guilty of rebellion, and treaſon,</hi> all the difference betwixt you and him is that what the poſtſcript would have done by St Andrewes upon himſelf in a juſt conſonancy to and punishment of his lying flattery, you would have the King for no cauſe to inflict on my friend as real demerit. But that which I concerne my ſelf moſt to notice, is the medium that you uſe to convince us of the truth of the Bishops po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, <hi>viz. that becauſe a ſubject committing a capital crime hath no right to be the executioner of juſtice on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, therefore his life is more in the Kings power then in his own</hi> but not to differ with you about thir pitieful words which were that <hi>all mens lives are in the Kings hand and hold of him,</hi> what ever agreement or place the argument may haue as to the Bishop, and amongſt his complices, perſons its like conſcious of their own guilt, yet ſure I am as all honeſt men are without the compaſſe of ſuch a title, ſo he muſt be a fool aſwell as a knave that will hold a plaine forfiture to the King
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:137225:21"/>to be a good tenor of him; the Bishop no doubt thought he had paſſed a great complement upon his Majeſty when by putting his life in the Kings power he gave more unto him then he hath himſelf, but when you come to be his interpreter how ſtrangely do you miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them both? <hi>the Bishop</hi> by ſuppoſing him to be criminal, and fo making him by right to amitt what he thought he had freely given, <hi>and the King,</hi> by preſenting him with nothing elſe then the forefei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lives of wretched catives in place of the loyal reſignation of free leiges; but leaving theſe your follies which if they had eſcaped my friend had no doubt been lashed by you as <hi>dull buffonries</hi> and the <hi>courſeſt of rallerie without either edge or point,</hi> the truth is our lives are not our own; <hi>all ſoules are mine ſaith the Lord,</hi> and therefore as we neither can give them up abſolutely unto the Prince his arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſpoſal, not hath the Lord even in the caſe of the moſt atro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious crime obliged the criminal to be <hi>felo deſe</hi> and his own execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, ſo all the power the Magiſtrat can pretend is onely founded in the ſentence of righteous Law, by which the perſon guiltie, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his right, is therefore both by the will of God, and his owne conſent ſubjected <hi>to the Magistrats</hi> execution and how much this doth militat both againſt the Bishops flatterie and the pretenſions of tyrannie all ſober men may preceive.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir in place of your examining my friends book in <hi>bulk,</hi> evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent enough by the <hi>groſſeneſſe</hi> of your reflexions, I have conſidered your Letter by <hi>retaile,</hi> wherein I am aſſured you will ſee that I have omitted to anſwer nothing except ſuch things as ſilence will beſt reprove, What ſatisfaction you will finde in my reply dependeth upon your ſelf: only in this I think I merit your acknowledgement that by my prevention I have delivered you our of my friends hands, who probably would have ſearched you out in a more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curat manner, if my ſineere endeavours shall produce to you any greater advantage, it is according to the ſerious deſire of one who though he hath no reaſon to be more, yet ſubſcribeth himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your real well-wisher.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>PAg. 6. lin. 3. read ſufferings. Pag. 9. l. 3. r. enough, p. 10. l. 1. r. doing. p. 17. l. 12. r. Skeens. p. 25. l. 1. r. this.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:137225:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
